Guide to the J.E. Wallace Sterling Personal Papers and Memorabilia
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
J.E. Wallace Sterling personal papers and memorabilia
1938-circa 1982
SC0415
Sterling, J. E. Wallace, (John Ewart Wallace), 1906-1985
5 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Scope and Contents
These personal papers and memorabilia, dating from 1939 to circa 1982, largely concern Sterling's years at Stanford University as president and chancellor, 1949 to circa 1982. Included are certificates, programs, clippings, diplomas, newsletters, albums, and photographs.
Access Terms
Bohemian Club (San Francisco, Calif.).; Stanford University -- General subdivision--Presidents.;; Stanford University. Overseas Study Program.; Albums.; College administrators.; Photoprints.; Scrapbooks; Stanford University--Administration.; Universities and colleges--Administration.
Collection Contents
- Original Accession
  - Biographical articles (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bohemian Club, "Wally Sterling Night", 1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - British knighthood (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - California Institute of Technology (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Certificates (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dinner programs (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Duke and Duchess of Glouchester at S.U., 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fresno State College commencement program; Sterling was speaker, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Glaser, Robert J., "The Medical Deanship"; inscribed to Sterling, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Greeting cards (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Luke, Florence, letter to Sterling, 3/26/1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Mark, Ian -sketches of Sterling (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Memorial service for Sterling, program (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous items (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Observations by Sterling on his appointment as Chancellor of S.U., 1968 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Palo Alto City, resolution, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Pasadena Jr. Chamber of Commerce testimonial, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Postcards to his daughters, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Stanford-in-Germany newsletter; inscribed to Sterling, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Stanford University, inauguration as president, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 10th anniversary as president, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Sterling, Ann -correspondence and clippings (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Sterling, J.E.Wallace, "Who is Clio? Where is She?" reprint, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Album presented to Sterling by representatives of faculty women of Academic Council, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Flanagan, Robert M. The Stock Certificate: Has the Paper Tiger Been Tamed? Master's thesis, Pace University, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Letters from Cliff Arquette. edited and annotated by Ken Darby, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    - A.A.U. and German rectors, 1964-07 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Alfalfa Club, Washington, DC, 1968-01-21 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Alumni party, Washington, DC, for Senator Carl Hayden (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Asia Foundation Conference, Hong Kong, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Board of Trustees, S.U. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Bohemian Club (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Bohemian Club (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Calgary Tigers (football team), 1930 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Canadian college events (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - CBS radio crew at Spreckels Sugar Factory (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Commencement scenes, S.U. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Council on Financing Higher Education, Texas (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Duke and Duchess of Glouchester at S.U., 1965 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Endowment presentations (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - The Family Farm Flight (birthday luncheons for Sterling, possibly at Bohemian Grove), 1952-1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Filoli ball, circa 1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Fire in president's office, S.U., 1968-07 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Fisher Body Craftsman Guild meeting (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Friends (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Gold Spike event (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Harvard law degree ceremony (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Hoover, Herbert with Sterling and others (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Hoover, Lou Henry (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Hoover House events (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Hoover House garden (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Huntington Library events (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - King of Belgium, visit to S.U. (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Los Angeles alumni fundraising event (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - McGill University, commencement (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Meyer Library, dedication (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - National War College, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Non-Stanford events (may include Stanford events that were off-campus) (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Paintings of J.E.Wallace Sterling (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Palo Alto real estate board (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Party for Jessie at Stockbridge house, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - President of Turkey in Los Angeles, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Red Cross events (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Retirement party, San Francisco, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - ROTC, president's review (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Seattle University, inauguration of Father John Fulteren (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Shell Directors' meeting, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Slides (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Snapshots and informal photographs (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Stanford events (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Stanford events (News & Pubs photographs) (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Stanford Center in Tokyo, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Stanford in Austria, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Stanford in Florence (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Stanford Research Institute (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - S.U. Medical Center -20th anniversary, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - S.U. Medical School -Mermer (?) dedication (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Sterling, Ann (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Sterling and Arlene Francis at Omar Khayyam's Restaurant, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Sterling and Chancellor Joset Klaus (Austrian), 1968 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Sterling and Sandra Day O'Connor (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Sterling and Sargent Shriver at Medical School (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Sterling at Annapolis, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Sterling at official events (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Sterling in Berlin (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Sterling on S.U. campus (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Sterling, portraits (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Sterling, unidentified (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Sterling family (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Sterlings at Philippines airport (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Sterlings, informal (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Sterlings, Lymans, Kennedys (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Terman, Fred E. (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Tokyo Stanford Club, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - University of British Columbia, Spring Congregation, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - University of Utah (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - White House, Bicentennial Commission reception (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Willow Creek apartments, ground-breaking, circa 1959 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Unidentified and Sterlings not in photographs (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Album of unidentified photos from a meeting (includes Sterling) (Box 4)
    - "Mark X plus IX" (Box 10)
      Photographs marking Sterling's 19 years as Stanford University president; this volume replaced the original Mark X volume, which was lost in the 1968 fire; includes signatures.
    - Oversize
      Album from 25th year celebration, 1974; Victoria College rugby team, 1939 (rolled); Hoover, Herbert--inscribed and autographed; formal occassions (degrees granted, board meetings, etc.); miscellaneous; portraits; Stanford University Board of Trustees.
  - Memorabilia (Box 5)
    Copper-clad box presented in honor of Dr. and Mrs. J. E. Wallace Sterling by Greater Area Stanford Clubs. 1968; various medals.
  - Diplomas (Box 6, 9)
  - Art (Box 7)
    Framed portrait, painting of Hoover House, wooden plaque.
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-1993-061
  - Sterling memoirs "The Stanford Presidency 1949-1968; Part II: A Noble Purpose Shared" (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sterling memoirs "The Stanford Presidency 1949-1968; Part III: Bits and Pieces" (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Sterling memoirs "The Stanford Presidency 1949-1968;] Some Extracurricular Activites" (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Sterling memoirs "The Stanford Presidency 1949-1968;] Part ill: Travelling ADeux and Otherwise" pp. 1-39 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - [Sterling memoirs "The Stanford Presidency 1949-1968;] Part ill: Travelling A Deux and Otherwise" pp. 40-100 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - [Sterling memoirs "The Stanford Presidency 1949-1968;] Part ill: Travelling A Deux and Otherwise" pp. 101-153 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-1993-074
  - Photographs: portraits of Sterling (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs: Sterling at events (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Diploma for Ph.D. at Stanford, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sterlings' guest book, 1949-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook of photographs, clippings, programs, and other miscellaneous items, primarily pertaining to his inauguration as Stanford's president, 1948-1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-1993-104
  - Contents Executive Committee Minutes, 1951-1958 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1965-1971 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1971-1977 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1978-1987 (Box 1)
  - Committee of the Department Minutes, 1973-1993 (Box 1)
  - English Department Meetings Minutes, 1965-1970 (Box 2)
  - English Department Meetings Minutes, 1969-1972 (Box 2)
  - Committee of the Faculty Minutes, 1970-1987 (Box 2)
  - Meetings of Full Professors Minutes, 1967-1987 (Box 2)